{"test_questions": [[{"question": "ZL = 200 &ohm; and it is desired that Zi = 50 &ohm; The quarter wave transformer should have a characteristic impedance of", "opta": "100 &ohm;", "optb": "40 &ohm;", "optc": "10000 &ohm;", "optd": "4 &ohm;", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Z0 = Zi . ZL"}, {"question": "A broadside array consisting of 200 cm wavelength with 10 half-wave dipole spacing 10 cm. And if each array element feeding with 1 amp. current and operating at same frequency then find the half power beamwidth", "opta": "4\u00b0", "optb": "2\u00b0", "optc": "10\u00b0", "optd": "15\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Refractive index of glass is 1.5. Find the wavelength of a beam of light with a frequency of 1014 Hz in glass. Assume velocity of light is 3 x 108 m/sec in vacuum.", "opta": "4 \u03bcm", "optb": "3 \u03bcm", "optc": "2 \u03bcm", "optd": "1 \u03bcm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Given, \u03bc = 1.6, f = 1014 Hz, v = 3 x 108 m/sec."}, {"question": "The function f(x - vot) represent which of the following?", "opta": "A stationary wave", "optb": "A wave motion in forward direction", "optc": "A wave motion in reverse direction", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "f(x - vot) represents in +ve direction while f(x + vot) represents a progressive wave in -ve direction."}, {"question": "A broadside array operating at 100 cm wavelength consist of 4 half-wave dipoles spaced 50 cm apart. Each element carries radio frequency current in the same phase and of magnitude 0.5 A. The radiated power will be", "opta": "196 W", "optb": "73 W", "optc": "36.5 W", "optd": "18.25 W", "ans": "A", "explanation": "P = n . I2 . Rr, where Rr = 80p2  &ohm;.\nn = 4."}, {"question": "The input impedance of short-circuited line of length l where \u03bb/4 < l < \u03bb/2, is", "opta": "resistive", "optb": "inductive", "optc": "capacitive", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "l < \u03bb/4, ZL = 0\n, if Zd comes +j kZC then inductive, \nIf Zd comes -j kZC then capacitive.\nfor 0 \u2264 l \u2264 1/4, \u03bb \u2264 l \u2264 3\u03bb/4 will be inductive."}, {"question": "A wave is propagated in a waveguide at frequency of 9 GHz and separation is 2 cm between walls find cut off wavelength for dominant mode.", "opta": "4 cm", "optb": "1 cm", "optc": "2 cm", "optd": "8 cm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Find the radiation resistance of an antenna of length \u03bb/10 meter?", "opta": "8 &ohm;", "optb": "780 &ohm;", "optc": "7.8 &ohm;", "optd": "78 &ohm;", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Charge needed within a unit sphere centred at the origin for producing a potential field,", "opta": "12 pc", "optb": "60 pc", "optc": "120 pc", "optd": "180 pc", "ans": "C", "explanation": "q = 120p coulomb, r = 1 meter."}, {"question": "A rectangular metal waveguide filled with a dielectric of relative permittivity \u03b5r = 4, has the inside dimensions 3 x 1.2 cm, the cut off frequency for the dominant mode is", "opta": "2.5 GHz", "optb": "5 GHz", "optc": "10 GHz", "optd": "12.5 GHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "for dominant mode."}, {"question": "A wave is propagated in a waveguide at frequency of 9 GHz and separation is 2 cm between walls Calculate group velocity for dominant mode.", "opta": "1.8 x 108 m/sec", "optb": "5 x 108 m/sec", "optc": "3 x 108 m/sec", "optd": "1.5 x 108 m/sec", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Vg . Vp = C2\nwhere \n."}, {"question": "For F1 layer the maximum ionic density is 2.3 x 104 electrons per cc. The critical frequency for this layer will be", "opta": "1.36 MHz", "optb": "13.6 MHz", "optc": "136 MHz", "optd": "1360 MHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "fc = 9Nmax ."}, {"question": "Which one of the following does represents the electric field lines for the TE02 mode in the cross section of a hollow rectangular metallic waveguide?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "TE02  m = 0, n = 2\nin x direction no propagation, only in y, and normal to the waveguide, tangential component is continuous."}, {"question": "The velocity of electromagnetic wave in a good conductor is", "opta": "3 x 108 m/s", "optb": "more than 3 x 108 m/s", "optc": "very low", "optd": "high", "ans": "C", "explanation": ", for good conductor \u03b5r >> 1."}, {"question": "Radiation intensity of a dipole depends strongly on frequency. If at a frequency f, the intensity of radiation is 'I'. Then at a frequency of f/2, the intensity will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I \u221d f."}, {"question": "Consider a 300 &ohm;, quarter wave long at 1 GHz transmission line as shown in figure. It is connected to a 10 V, 50 &ohm; source at one end is left open circuited at the other end. The magnitude of the voltage at the open circuit end of the line is", "opta": "10 V", "optb": "5 V", "optc": "60 V", "optd": "60/7 volt", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\u03b3 = a + j\u03b2 a = 0  \u03b3 = j\u03b2\nPropagating wave\nv = VI e-rz + VR erz\nNo change in the voltage at the open end it will same, \nvr = 10 volt."}, {"question": "The phase angle corresponding to \u03bb/4 in a standing-wave pattern is", "opta": "30\u00b0", "optb": "90\u00b0", "optc": "135\u00b0", "optd": "180\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A hollow rectangular waveguide has dimensions a = 2b. Calculate the amount of attenuation, if the frequency is 3 GHz, and b = 1 cm.", "opta": "49", "optb": "47.33", "optc": "50.33", "optd": "50", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since, wave is attenuated hence \u03b2 = 0\nand  Take, dominant mode m = 1, \nn = 0\n ."}, {"question": "Calculate the directivity of an antenna for \u03b8E = 30\u00b0, \u03b8H = 60", "opta": "46", "optb": "23", "optc": "50", "optd": "100", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Most antenna consisting of a 50 meter long vertical conductor operates over a perfectly conducting ground plane. It is base fed at a frequency of 600 kHz. The radiation resistance of the antenna in ohms is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "20p2", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A (75 - j 40) W load is connected to a co-axial line of z0 = 75\u03c9 at 6 MHz. The load matching on the line can be accomplished by connecting", "opta": "a short circuit stub at the load", "optb": "an inductance at the load", "optc": "a short circuit stub at a specific distance from the load", "optd": "a capacitance at a specific distance from the load", "ans": "B", "explanation": "ZL = 75 - J . 40, ZC = 75 W, f = 6 mHz\nGiven ZL is capacitive, so proper matching, load must be inductive."}, {"question": "A plane wave is characterized by  the wave is", "opta": "linearly polarized", "optb": "circularly polarized", "optc": "elliptically polarized", "optd": "unpolarized", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Because, magnitude is different (0.5, 1) and phase is 90\u00b0"}, {"question": "The electric field on the surface of a perfect conductor is 2V/m. The conductor is immersed in water with \u03b5 = 80 \u03b50. The surface charge density on the conductor is ((\u03b50 = 10-9/36p)F/m)", "opta": "0 c/m2", "optb": "2 c/m2", "optc": "1.8 x 10-11 c/m2", "optd": "1.14 x 10-9 c/m2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A wave is propagated in a waveguide at frequency of 9 GHz and separation is 2 cm between walls calculate the phase velocity for dominant mode.", "opta": "3 x 108 m/sec", "optb": "5 x 108 m/sec", "optc": "1.5 x 108 m/sec", "optd": "9 x 108 m/sec", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Vg . Vp = C2\nwhere ."}, {"question": "A plane electromagnetic wave travels in dielectric medium of relative permittivity 9. Relative to free space, the velocity of propagation in the dielectric is", "opta": "increased by a factor of 9", "optb": "increased by a factor of 3", "optc": "unchanged", "optd": "reduced by a factor of 1/3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Consider a loss less antenna with a directive gain of + 6 dB. If 1 mW of power is fed to it the total power radiated by the antenna will be", "opta": "4 mW", "optb": "1 mW", "optc": "7 mW", "optd": "1/4 mW", "ans": "A", "explanation": "6 dB = 10 log10 \n = 100.6  3.98\nPr = 3.98 mW."}, {"question": "A uniform plane wave is one in which", "opta": "x  = 0", "optb": ".", "optc": "and  are perpendicular", "optd": "and  lie in a plane", "ans": "D", "explanation": "For uniform plane wave, E and H must be in a plane but perpendicular to each other."}, {"question": "The electric field of the incident wave is , where \u03c9 = 3 x 109p and \u03b2 = 10 p. The electric field of the transmitted wave Et is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In, question, it is not mentioned, about medium; dielectric etc.\nEi = Et + Er \n Et = Er \n Et =  Ei."}, {"question": "A short circuited stub is shunt connected to a transmission line as shown in the figure is, if z0 = 500 ohms, the admittance y seen at the function of the stub and the transmission line is", "opta": "(0.01 - j 0.02) mho", "optb": "(0.02 - j 0.01) mho", "optc": "(0.04 - j 0.02) mho", "optd": "(0.02 + j 0) mho", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following should dominant wave have?", "opta": "Lowest cut off frequency", "optb": "Highest cut off frequency", "optc": "No attenuation", "optd": "No phase shift", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Lowest cut off frequency or highest wave-length in a waveguide gives dominant modes."}, {"question": "Calculate the wave impedance for TM mode in rectangular waveguide for dominant mode at 3 GHz having", "opta": "(120p) &ohm;", "optb": "377 &ohm;", "optc": "226 &ohm;", "optd": "629 &ohm;", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u03b7 = 226 &ohm;."}, {"question": "The divergence of the electric field intensity at any point equals", "opta": "1/4 p\u03b50 times the volume charge density", "optb": "l/\u03b50 times the volume charge density at that point", "optc": "\u03b50 times the volume charge density at that point", "optd": "the volume charge density at that point", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "For a 400 kHz transmission line having L = 0.5 mH/km, C = 0.08 mF and negligible R and G, the value of propagation constant P will be", "opta": "15.9 radians/km", "optb": "31.8 radians/km", "optc": "63.6 radians/km", "optd": "105.4 radians/km", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\u03b3 = a + j\u03b2, a = 0 \u03b2 = \u03c9LC."}, {"question": "The Depth of penetration of EM wave in medium having conductivity \u03c3 at a frequency of 1 MHz is 25 cm. The depth of penetration at a frequency of 4 MHz will be", "opta": "6.25 cm", "optb": "12.50 cm", "optc": "50 cm", "optd": "100 cm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Skin depth \n\n \u03b42 = \u03b41/2 ."}, {"question": "What is the characteristic impedance at 10 MHz?", "opta": "547.7 &ohm;", "optb": "54.7 &ohm;", "optc": "5.47 &ohm;", "optd": ".547 &ohm;", "ans": "A", "explanation": ", not depend upon frequency."}, {"question": "The torque (in mm) acting on a circular current loop of radius 1 mm in the xy plane, connected at the origin and with current 0.1 A, flowing in the sense of increasing in a magnetic field  is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "10-12p", "optd": "- 10-12p", "ans": "B", "explanation": "t = M x B"}, {"question": "Which one of the following potential does not satisfy Laplace's equations?", "opta": "v = 10 xy", "optb": "v = p cos \u03c6", "optc": "", "optd": "v = f cos \u03c6 + 10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A rectangular waveguide measures 3 x 4.5 cm internally and has a 10 GHz signal propagated in it. Calculate the wave impedance for dominant mode.", "opta": "130 p", "optb": "1.3 p", "optc": "120 p", "optd": "12 p", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Wave impedance  \n."}, {"question": "Calculate wave impedance for TE mode", "opta": "(377)&ohm;", "optb": "226 &ohm;", "optc": "\u221e", "optd": "629 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a 100 turn coil, if the flux through each turn is (t3 - 2t)mWb, the magnitude of the induced emf in the coil at a time of 4 sec is", "opta": "46 mV", "optb": "56 mV", "optc": "4.6 V", "optd": "5.6 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "E = 100 (3t2 - 2)  100(46)  4600 mV\n 4.6 V."}, {"question": "A transmission line is feeding 1 watt of power to a horn antenna having a gain of 10 dB. The antenna is matched to the transmission line. The total power radiated by the horn antenna into the free space is", "opta": "10 watts", "optb": "1 watt", "optc": "0.1 watt", "optd": "0.01 watt", "ans": "A", "explanation": "= 101  Pr = 10 watt."}, {"question": "A parallel polarized wave is incident from air into paraffin having relative permittivity 3, the value of its Brewster angle is", "opta": "0\u00b0", "optb": "30\u00b0", "optc": "45\u00b0", "optd": "60\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Brewster angle \u03b8 = tan-1 ."}, {"question": "In a conductor which of the following relations hold good?", "opta": "\u2207 x D = r", "optb": "\u2207 . D = r", "optc": "\u2207 x D = 0", "optd": "\u2207 . D = 0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Inside a conductor free charge is zero, hence, \u2207 x D = 0."}, {"question": "The radiation resistance of a \u03bb/16 wire dipole in free space will be nearly", "opta": "1 &ohm;", "optb": "3 &ohm;", "optc": "13 &ohm;", "optd": "30 &ohm;", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Rr = 80p2."}, {"question": "Two identical antennas are placed in the \u03b8 = p/2 plane as shown in the figure. The elements have equal amplitude excitation with 180\u00b0 polarity difference, operating of the far-zone resultant electric field strength normalized with that of a single element, both computed for \u03c6 = 0, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Normalised array factor = n cos \n\nwhere \u03c6 is the phase difference.\n \u03c6 = (\u03b2d sin \u03b8 cos \u03c6 + \u03b81)\nand \u03b8 = 90\u00b0, \u03c6 = 45\u00b0"}, {"question": "Find the noise factor for an antenna at 27\u00b0C with equivalent noise temperature 30\u00b0K", "opta": "20", "optb": "100", "optc": "300", "optd": "1.1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Te = T0(F - 1)\n ."}, {"question": "The displacement flux density at a point on the surface of a perfect conductor is  = 2(ax - 3 az)c/m2 pointing away from the surface. The charge density at that point c/m2 will be", "opta": "2", "optb": "- 2", "optc": "4", "optd": "- 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2207 . D = r."}, {"question": "Characteristic impedance of a transmission line is 50 &ohm;. Input impedance of the open circuited line. Zoc = 100 + J150 &ohm;. When transmission line is short circuited, then value of the input impedance will be", "opta": "50 &ohm;", "optb": "100 + J150 &ohm;", "optc": "7.69 + J11.54&ohm;", "optd": "7.69 - J11.54 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "ZC = ZOC - ZSC  50 = (100 + j150)(ZSC) ."}]]}